<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands second alarm to vvar, against the Beast. Saul, with his Edomite has shed blood to his power; he smites Israels city, and destroyes his owne house; overcame his people once, and overthrew himselfe for ever! It relates to what is done now. Grave questions touching the Edomite; his admission to court, and into office there; how it relates to papists now. He has a commission to destroy a city of priests, which he does with an utter destruction. Excellent reasons why the Lord suffered such a destruction to be executed upon Israel then; and why he suffers the same now; and why by an Edomites hand then and now.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3047</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E59_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23537</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872032</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872032</idno>
            <idno type="VID">155295</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84000)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 155295)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 10:E59[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands second alarm to vvar, against the Beast. Saul, with his Edomite has shed blood to his power; he smites Israels city, and destroyes his owne house; overcame his people once, and overthrew himselfe for ever! It relates to what is done now. Grave questions touching the Edomite; his admission to court, and into office there; how it relates to papists now. He has a commission to destroy a city of priests, which he does with an utter destruction. Excellent reasons why the Lord suffered such a destruction to be executed upon Israel then; and why he suffers the same now; and why by an Edomites hand then and now.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Vnderhil, in the second yeare of the Beasts wounding, warring against the Lamb, and those that are with him, called, chosen, and faithfull,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: Englands alarm to war.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "10 July".</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 1st, XIX-XXXI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:155295:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:155295:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLANDS <hi>SECOND</hi> Alarm to VVar, Againſt the Beaſt. <hi>Saul,</hi> with his Edomite has ſhed blood to his power; He ſmites Iſraels City, and deſtroyes his owne houſe; overcame his People once, and overthrew himſelfe for ever! It relates to what is done now. Grave queſtions touching the <hi>Edomite;</hi> his admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to Court, and into office there; how it relates to Papiſts now. He has a Commiſsion to deſtroy a City of Prieſts, which he does with an utter deſtruction. Excellent Reaſons why The <hi>Lord</hi> ſuffered ſuch a deſtruction to be executed upon Iſrael then; And why he ſuffers the ſame now; And why by an <hi>Edomites</hi> hand then and now.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Lament. 4.21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Rejoyce and be glad <hi>[It is a bitter mockery,</hi> i.e. <hi>weepe and howle]</hi> O Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Edom, The Cup alſo ſhall paſſe thorow unto thee: Thou ſhalt be drunken, and ſhalt make thy ſelfe naked.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 49.25.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For thus ſaith The LORD, The prey of the Terrible ſhall be delivered; I will contend with him that contendeth with Thee; I will feed them, that ſpoile Thee, with their owne fleſh, and they ſhall be drunken with their owne blood as with ſweet wine.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Vnderhil,</hi> in the ſecond yeare of the Beaſts wounding warring againſt The Lamb and thoſe that are with Him, <hi>Called, Choſen,</hi> and <hi>Faithfull.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:155295:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:155295:2"/>
            <head>ENGLANDS ALARM TO VVar, againſt the Beaſt.</head>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT.</hi> II. THe <hi>Edomite</hi> is <hi>Sauls</hi> Scout now, and his Generall in the Field anon: <hi>Davids</hi> enemy alwaies, The Prieſts accuſer; but can charge him with no more but what was his office to do, therefore not ſo impudent as are the <hi>Edomites</hi> in our dayes: <hi>Saul</hi> impleads the Prieſt; gives him leave to make anſwer for himſelfe, which he doth clearly and fully; and then is deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he, and a City of Prieſts, man, woman, and childe there, and beaſt alſo. This relates fully to our times. Quaeries touching the <hi>Edomite. Sauls</hi> taking him into his Court, aſsigning him to office there, and giving him commiſsion to ſmite a City of Prieſts. Quaeries touching that miſerable deſtruction. Gods judgements ſecret, but juſt and righteous upon <hi>Ireland,</hi> and <hi>England.</hi> Yet the miſchiefe done by man ſhall returne upon his owne head, and his violent dealing upon his owne pate.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:155295:3"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. I. David</hi> comes to <hi>Nob; Doeg</hi> ſpies him there; haſtens to <hi>Saul,</hi> tels him all his obſervations, yet can lay nothing to the Prieſts charge, but what was the Prieſts duty to doe. <hi>Doeg</hi> tels truth, yet loved <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> The <hi>Edomites</hi> now, more ſhameleſſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Avid</hi> comes to <hi>Nob</hi> to <hi>Abimelech</hi> the Prieſt there,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.</note> intreats a courteſie of him, and the Prieſt does him a Hawfull favour (whereof we ſhall heare more anon) <hi>Doeg</hi> the <hi>Edomite, Sauls</hi> chiefe Heardſman was there, for <hi>Saul</hi> had a Scout to ſpy every where, but none did his maſter better ſervice (to <hi>Sauls</hi> liking) then <hi>Doeg</hi> did; he was an <hi>Edomite,</hi> (that I would have noted) and now, being in <hi>Iſraels</hi> Land, he was of his Religion too [for that is a thing eaſily taken up] and being at <hi>Nob,</hi> has a faire pretence for that alſo, as you may reade, Religion called him thither, and held him there: a pretence only, and no more; for that bloudy wretch mindes not Religion, not the ſolemne Acts thereabout: he mindes only all that which paſſed betwixt <hi>Abimeleth</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> that ſo he might doe miſchiefe, <hi>a mighty man that way.</hi> And now having fed his eye, and filled his mouth with obſervations, hee haſtened to his maſter <hi>Saul,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.6.</note> findes him <hi>in Gibeah under a tree in Ramah, having his ſpeare in his hand, and all his ſervants ſtanding about him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is worth the noting by the way, what miſchiefe this evill and perverſe <hi>will</hi> actuated by his evill ſpirit, has done unto <hi>Saul;</hi> It had drowne him from his owne houſe, and Court, where he might have reſted in peace with his ſervants about him; he is now, even <hi>Saul</hi> the King, under a Tree with a ſpeare in his hand, when no enemy is neere him but himſelfe, and his evill ſpirit, which he entertaines and hugges as his beſt friend, though the worſt enemy to <hi>Saul,</hi> next to himſelfe, and the peace of the kingdome. It is a true ſaying. A man findes no ſuch enemy in the world, as he may finde himſelfe to be to himſelfe.<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> The Greek Father has a full Treatiſe upon that matter: I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the <hi>Tree</hi> againe, where <hi>Doeg</hi> found his maſter, him, that had loſt himſelfe, and heard him complaine bitterly to his ſervants, That they had <hi>all conſpired againſt him.</hi> Why? becauſe they had not yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed innocent <hi>David,</hi> and delivered him as a prey up unto their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters hands: This <hi>Saul</hi> calls a <hi>conſpiracy</hi> with his ſonne <hi>Ionathan,</hi> a good man, who withholds his fathers hands as long as he could from ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding innocent bloud, and does, according to Gods Commandement, his utmoſt to deliver the innocent; This <hi>Saul</hi> calls a ſtirring up his ſervant (he meanes <hi>David</hi>) againſt him,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 9.</note> 
                     <hi>to lye in wait as at this day.</hi> It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:155295:3"/>
                     <hi>Then anſwered Doeg.</hi> The Edomite takes the words out of <hi>Sauls</hi> mouth, as ſpoken to himſelfe: they were very pleaſing to him, and anſwers before he was asked, for ſure <hi>Saul</hi> does not queſtion the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites readineſſe in that ſervice. But he anſwers, aſſureth <hi>Saul,</hi> that hee is none of thoſe conſpirators with <hi>Ionathan,</hi> in behalfe of <hi>David,</hi> not he; and he gives good teſtimony thereof, for he tells all that, which paſſed betwixt <hi>Abimelech</hi> and <hi>David</hi> there; he tells all, juſt as <hi>David</hi> knew it would be, when he heard that <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite had ſpied him there.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 22.</note> We may obſerve <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalme touching this matter; and by the way, <hi>how well fitted a cruell maſter is with a bloudy ſervant.</hi> And ſo let it paſſe;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.</note> noting only this in this place, and touching that Edomite; how <hi>Doeg</hi> impleads <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and what he layes to his charge; he tells all, and yet he tels nothing at all, but what ſtands upon everlaſting record to the Edomites ſhame, and the Prieſts glory: for this he ſayes, <hi>I ſaw the ſonne of Ieſſe,</hi> [he meanes <hi>David</hi>] but ſpeakes as contemptibly of him as he thought fit at that time; yet not ſo wickedly as the Edomites now adayes call <hi>David,</hi> for they call him by as vile a name as <hi>David,</hi> vile in his owne eyes, but the more pretious in Gods eyes, cals himſelfe, a <hi>dog.</hi>]</p>
                  <p>I ſaw <hi>the ſonne of Ieſſe come to Nob to Abimelech there.</hi> [Well,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.9.</note> whither ſhould <hi>David</hi> goe, perſecuted by a cruell Lord, but to a good Prieſt for direction from <hi>Gods</hi> mouth? there was no hurt, but good in all that] <hi>The Prieſt enquired of the Lord for him.</hi>] [It was well he did, for hee did but his duty,] and <hi>gave David bread.</hi>] The Prieſt was bound to doe as much to his enemy, much more to <hi>David,</hi> for who ſo faithfull as <hi>David</hi> in all the kingdome. Nay, had he not done it (though ſacred bread) he had deſtroyed <hi>David;</hi> as bloudy men have done in <hi>Oxford,</hi> denying the hungry ſoule bread there, and ſuffering them to dye for want of water.] And <hi>gave David the ſword of Goliab the Philiſtine.</hi> [And that was it, but the greateſt reaſon for that in the world. <hi>David</hi> had ſlaine the Philiſtine with the ſword, then carries it away as lawfull <hi>prize;</hi> but, that <hi>God</hi> might have all the glory, he layes it up before the <hi>Lord;</hi> and now, after enquiring at <hi>Gods</hi> mouth, it is given <hi>David.</hi>] But this is all the Edomite has to ſay; And I know not what he could have ſaid more to the Prieſt his commendation. Bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> that the Edomite has not whereof to accuſe the good Prieſt; all he ſpeaks is for his commendation; and ſurely ſo is <hi>the will of God,</hi> that, with well doing, Prieſts then, and Miniſters now, and people alſo (and it is their glory) may put to ſilence,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16.</note> [muzzle the mouths of beaſtly men] we reade, <hi>ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men.</hi> And ſo, by the will and grace of <hi>God,</hi> have and doe Miniſters, and people at this day, even put to ſilence the ignorance of wicked men: Many and grievious things are laid to their charge, but no more proved then was againſt <hi>David</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:155295:4"/>or <hi>Paul</hi> after him. Therefore wee muſt note here, that the Edomite then, though a bloudy wretch, and mighty to doe miſchief, and could, like the Spider, turne Balſome into Poiſon; yet was he a very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt informer: I doe not remember, that the Biſhops had ſuch ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any of their Courts; and truly he ſhames the Edomites of theſe dayes: This Edomite tels <hi>Saul</hi> the truth, and nothing but the truth, and ſo ſhames the Devill: That <hi>Abimelech enquired of the Lord for Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> ſo he did; <hi>That he gave David bread;</hi> ſo he did too: <hi>and a ſword;</hi> ſo he did alſo. The Edomite accuſeth the Prieſt of no more but what the Prieſt did, and the Edomite ſaw done. The children of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in theſe daies are more graceleſſe and impudent a great deale: they ſweare, and curſe; and blaſpheme, and doe not utter more words then lyes, againſt <hi>David,</hi> the upright in heart; what devouring words heare we from their mouthes! what horrible blaſphemies from <hi>Liechfields</hi> Preſſe in <hi>Oxford!</hi> how doe they charge <hi>David</hi> with thoſe things he knowes not? nay abhorres to thinke of, as contrary to his foule and ſpirit, as were thoſe things charged upon <hi>Iob</hi> in his two and twentieth Chapter.</p>
                  <p>This is all wee will note, touching the <hi>Edomite</hi> in this Chapter; we ſhall enquire more of him anon. We ſee here, he was a very man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly civill fellow, in compariſon of the <hi>Edomites</hi> now a dayes; not ſo much of the Divill in him as theſe have, who rage now amongſt us, breaking bands, and caſting away cords, as poſſeſſed men in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient times. And yet before I ſhut up this Chapter, I muſt ſatisfie a ſmall doubt.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.3.</note> 
                     <hi>David</hi> in his Pſalme of Inſtructions, tells us that <hi>Doeg loved ſying;</hi> So hee did, for when <hi>Saul</hi> complained, that all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants <hi>conſpired</hi> againſt him;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="6 letters">
                              <desc>••••••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Edomite,</hi> and this time.</note> they do indeed, ſaid <hi>Doeg, Abimelech conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth</hi> againſt thee too; and ſo he accuſeth the Prieſt, <hi>materially,</hi> not one falſe word in the whole Accuſation: But <hi>intentionally,</hi> lyes all, and devouring words; he intended as much miſchiefe to <hi>Abimelech,</hi> as hee could have done him, had he ſpoken againſt him never a word true. We may exemplifie it thus.</p>
                  <p>An <hi>Edomite</hi> now, (for we ſhall prove anon, that the <hi>Papiſt</hi> now, and the <hi>Edomites</hi> then, are brothers) came to the King, tells his Majeſtie, that the Ammunition was removed from <hi>Hull.</hi> That is true; and yet lying and devouring words, intentionally ſpoke to enrage the King againſt his beſt Subjects. It is all in all with what minde words are ſpoken, if with a mind to murther and deſtroy, they are lying and devouring words, though never a word falſe: and ſo I will ſhut up this Chapter,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ</hi> 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou loveſt all devouring words, O deceitfull man!</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:155295:4"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. II. Saul</hi> impleads <hi>Abimelech;</hi> he makes anſwer for himſelfe, which clears the caſe of all the righteous now, and the great caſe now in queſtion. <hi>Saul</hi> is not ſatisfied with reaſon, but, notwithstanding reaſon and Law both, command alſo from Gods mouth for what <hi>Abimelech</hi> did, <hi>Saul</hi> ſlayeth <hi>Abimelech,</hi> and deſtroy's the City of Prieſts.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SAul</hi> will be diſcovered anon, his owne hand will take off the Vaile, wherewith he has covered the eyes of Prieſts and People: the very intents of his heart touching <hi>David</hi> will be laid naked before the people; his owne hand will now give in cleare evidence, how bloody his thoughts were alwayes towards <hi>David.</hi> And indeed the hand is a ſure witneſſe, and tells us evermore whitherto thoughts tend, as the caſting the Water-mans Armes tells us whither hee tends, and not the ſetting of his face. When <hi>Diotrephes</hi> did reach forth his hand to Excommunication, caſting the Brethren out of the Church, then the old Servant of the Lord muſt needs tell againſt whom the malitious words were pointed or <hi>prated; Againſt us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">3. <hi>Epiſt. Ioh.</hi> 10. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſaith Saint <hi>John,</hi> for againſt them the hand went our alſo. I ſpeak not this, as if I thought it ſo hard a matter to ken which way malicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring words doe tend; or that I thinke the thoughts, projects, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of the wicked againſt the godly are ſo indiſcernable; though we muſt grant that there are many intricacies and perplexities in their wayes, the turnings and windings of the crooked Serpent; for the wicked (like harmfull beaſts) doe love <hi>confuſa veſtigia.</hi> The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man forgeth and hammereth forth deceit,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Fabricatur, Pro.</hi> 6.14.</note> and while his thoughts and imaginations are thus buſily employed, he thinks no eye is upon him, but that he is (as ſome Pioner or Gun-powder-man) hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ground: and indeed from the eye of man hee is hid. For our thoughts are but the tranſactions or diſcuſſions of the minde, within that inward cloſet and privie Chamber there, and therefore they muſt needs want forme and ſhape; but the office of the tongue is to ſtamp a forme, to give a ſhape unto them, and then our thoughts are le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible.</p>
                  <p>For what other are our actions, but our very thoughts, our ſecret talkings and parleys of our minde, caſt into a mould: onely we muſt obſerve (and it is but a common obſervation) That the hand giveth the trueſt ſhape, the hand maketh the perfecteſt mould. There are ſome, we know, who read not as they write, nor ſing as they pricke,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:155295:5"/>and many more who ſpeake not as they thinke; but the hand varieth not from the <hi>Idea</hi> that was in the minde. If a man forgeth miſchiefe upon his bed, then when he is up, and it be in the power of his hands, and there be no over-ruling hand, he will act it: The hand is a ſure interpreter of our mind, and of the tranſactions there, an infallible witneſſe that cannot lie: words may deceive, and many times are ſpoken for this very end, to darken the thoughts and intent of the mind, and to make them leſſe legible; theſe may be <hi>ſmoother then but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> when <hi>warre is in his heart:</hi> theſe may be as <hi>ſoft as oyle,</hi> and yet <hi>drawn ſwords,</hi> as we read: But when we ſee the hand beſmeared with bloud, then we certainly conclude, that the thoughts were of a ſcarlet co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour; and this is the ſight or proſpect we ſhall take a view of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, A bloudy execution done upon <hi>Nob,</hi> yet bloudy though it be, <hi>Saul</hi> pretends hee does it by helpe of God and the Law, by the knowne Lawes of the Kingdome; which, that we may examine, we will handle it not as an <hi>execution</hi> done, but ready to be done, elſe <hi>Saul</hi> might be ſaid to doe as the Judge at <hi>Lidford,</hi> who hanged a man in the forenoone, and then heard his inditement, and paſſed ſentence over him in the afternoone, not called the <hi>knowne Law</hi> of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome then,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Iueil. defence.</note> but <hi>Lidford Law</hi> to this day. <hi>Saul</hi> was not to bad as to do ſo, he hath ſlaine <hi>Abimelech,</hi> but hee impleaded him firſt, objects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and heares what hee can ſay for himſelfe: <hi>Saul</hi> hath this to ſay againſt him.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>Abimelech</hi> and the ſon of <hi>Ieſſe</hi> (<hi>Saul</hi> meanes <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Ob.</note> whom hee names with as little honour as can be) were confederate together and had conſpired againſt him;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.13.</note> 
                     <hi>Why have ye conſpired againſt me, thou and the ſonne of Ieſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſore accuſation,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> but of no weight, validity, or ſtrength, from <hi>Sauls</hi> mouth, who calls all conſpirators, who will not ſhew <hi>Saul</hi> where <hi>David</hi> is, that ſo he may ſhed innocent bloud according to the power in his hands,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 8.</note> that ſo he may ſhed innocent bloud according to the power in his hands,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.</note> 
                     <hi>All of you have conſpired againſt me.</hi> But what had the Prieſt done which might be called a <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> a taking part with <hi>David, That he ſhould riſe againſt Saul, to lye in wait as it is at this day?</hi> Thus <hi>Saul</hi> ſayes, and ſo he impleads <hi>Abimelech.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In that thou haſt given bread,</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Ob.</note> 
                     <hi>and a ſword, and haſt enquired of God for him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We will take the laſt firſt,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> 
                     <hi>enquired of God for David:</hi> It was the Prieſts office ſo to do; nor was that the firſt time that the Prieſt enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of the Lord for <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15.</note> nor did the Prieſt know the ſecond amongſt the many thouſands of Iſrael, who deſerved better from the hands of <hi>Saul</hi> and all Iſrael then <hi>Dauid</hi> did; and therefore why might not <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> enquire of the Lord for him There is all Reaſon and Law both, that ſo the Prieſt ſhould doe, enquire of the Lord for <hi>David;</hi> but
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:155295:5"/>reaſon will not ſerve, nor the reſolution of the Lord neither. The enquiry was (ſaith <hi>Iunius</hi>) about the <hi>Shew-bread,</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Vt cognoſeeree an ſacros panes tantùm Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus conceſſos, &amp; gladium ſemel Deo ſacratum, ad alios uſus tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre fas eſſet.</note> lawfull for the Prieſts onely to eat; and the <hi>Sword</hi> conſecrated to God, <hi>Whether that or this might be tranſlated unto other uſes?</hi> whereunto (no doubt) the Prieſt had full ſatisfaction, That they might; In ſuch an extremity <hi>David</hi> might refreſh his hungry ſoule with that bread; and in ſuch a danger which God was privie to, hee might take <hi>Goliah</hi> ſword, to defend himſelf therewith; and to prevent <hi>Saul</hi> from ſeizing upon it firſt,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21 10.</note> the more eaſily thereby to further his bloudy deſigne upon <hi>David.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But yet there is ſome more queſtion touching the <hi>Sword;</hi> as for the <hi>bread,</hi> it was made for man, and not man for bread: That is a cleared caſe from the Lord Chriſts owne mouth. Touching the Sword there is all the queſtion now: <hi>Saul</hi> (a King) pretends himſelfe Maſter of the ſame, as of <hi>Keilah;</hi> for all the ſtrong holds and ammunition there did belong to <hi>Saul,</hi> they were all his proper goods, and therefore <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech</hi> giving the ſword to <hi>David,</hi> he did it, that he ſhould uſe it againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> to lye in wait: So <hi>Saul</hi> forceth the accuſation.</p>
                  <p>Whereunto <hi>Abimeleth</hi> makes a faire and full anſwer: That <hi>Saul</hi> was no more <hi>Lord</hi> of the one then of the other; he had no more propriety or right in the <hi>ſword</hi> then in the <hi>bread;</hi> nor the one, nor the other were <hi>Sauls,</hi> but the <hi>Lords,</hi> laid-up both before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Him: But the <hi>Lord</hi> hath no nead of <hi>bread</hi> or of a <hi>ſword.</hi> His people Iſrael have need of both; and as their need required, ſo Iſrael might take the Bread, thereby to ſuſtaine life, and the Sword, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to defend life. <hi>David</hi> tooke it for that end, and according to the minde and will of God, whoſe intent was cleare. That <hi>Goliabs</hi> ſword, now lawfully wreſted out of his hand, and in <hi>Davids</hi> hand, then lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up before the Lord, ſhould be for the defence of Iſrael, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie Iſrael againſt their enemies to the worlds end. And ſo the caſe is reſolved about <hi>Keilah</hi> too, a City that had gates and bartes, not <hi>Sauls</hi> City now to batter downe (though he would preſume ſo farre) about <hi>Davids</hi> eares; but His City whoſe the kingdome was, the Lords kingdome, and truſted onely to <hi>Saul</hi> for the defence of Iſrael, and no further: And yet that <hi>Abimelech</hi> may deliver no more to <hi>Saul</hi> but what is juſtifiable by the Law of heaven and earth, he aſſureth him, that what he ſayes is from Gods Mouth, for there he enquired, and received anſwer as aforeſaid, and thereupon his warrant to give <hi>David Bread</hi> and <hi>Sword</hi> both. Moreover he addes, <hi>be it far from him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.14.</note> the Prieſt of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to entertaine a diſloyall thought againſt his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the <hi>Lords</hi> Anointed, enquiring of the Lord for <hi>David,</hi> and giving him <hi>bread</hi> and a <hi>ſword:</hi> he knew <hi>David</hi> to be a faithfull perſon, none like him in all <hi>Sauls</hi> houſe, nor more honourable, being the Kings Son-in-Law, and for any thing elſe hee knew nothing <hi>leſſe or more.</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:155295:6"/>As honeſt and ſatisfying an anſwere, had it been ſpoken to any mans eare but <hi>Sauls,</hi> as ever came from a Prieſts mouth, for it was taken from Gods Mouth: but <hi>Saul</hi> is reſolved before hand upon the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, for nothing can ſatisfie <hi>Sauls</hi> thirſt but <hi>Davids</hi> bloud; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Abimelech</hi> ſtood in <hi>Sauls</hi> way, and for reliefe of <hi>David, Saul</hi> will have the Prieſts bloud;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſ.</hi> 16.</note> 
                     <hi>And the King ſaid, thou ſhalt ſurely dye Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech:</hi> See! There is an argument <hi>Abimelech</hi> cannot anſwere: when a man drives furiouſly onward in a bloudy way, neither law nor rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhall ſtop him, nor the Angel with his drawne ſword in the way. Nay, <hi>Saul</hi> ſtops not there, he ſpeaks more bloudy words yet, and will doe as he ſpeakes: What? I am loth to mention it from the mouth of a King, and King of Iſrael, the great <hi>Fiductary</hi> of the kingdome there; I had rather a Philiſtin ſaid it, ſuch an unkingly word, ſo devoid of all reaſon and humanity: but yet Iſraels King ſayes it, and we muſt repeat it after him, <hi>Thou, and all thy fathers houſe:</hi> Ah Lord! what a bloudy word is this! what a bloudy man is that! An <hi>Evill ſpirit</hi> came upon <hi>Saul</hi> indeed, haunts him ſtill, and drives him on: <hi>Lord</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us from him, for the man is mad with rage, <hi>Thou, and all thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.23.</note> True it is it was the burden of the <hi>Lord</hi> upon <hi>Elies</hi> houſe, and cauſe there was juſt enough, why God ſhould doe to that houſe as he threatned. Yea and juſt cauſe too, though not ſo cleare to dim eyes, Wherefore <hi>Nob</hi> ſhould be ſo ſmitten, men, women, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren there. We have concluded, The cauſe is juſt, for God is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; And yet no cauſe, not the leaſt title of reaſon, why <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould doe it, why he ſhould ſeale a Commiſſion to an <hi>Edomite</hi> to doe ſuch an horrible execution; <hi>Saul</hi> (I ſay) the great <hi>Eiductary</hi> of the kingdom, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with the lives of all the Prieſts &amp; people there, no reaſon why <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould ſo ſay, and ſo do, being as aforeſaid; but all the reaſon in the world why he ſhould <hi>ſtop his eare from hearing of bloud,</hi> much more his hand from ſhedding the ſame. But <hi>Saul</hi> will do as he ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt ſurely dye Abimelech, thou and all thy fathers houſe:</hi> See! <hi>Saul</hi> will be chief and fore-man in this bloudy worke, to make the City of Prieſts an <hi>Acheldama,</hi> that it may be called no more <hi>Nob,</hi> but a <hi>Field of bloud,</hi> or HORMAH,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 21.3.</note> 
                     <hi>utter deſtruction. Saul</hi> is the chiefe Actor here, for he commands his ſervants firſt, <hi>Turne ye and ſlay the Prieſts;</hi> his ſervants would not; <hi>Saul</hi> will have it done: then he turned to <hi>Doeg</hi> a <hi>Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and ſaid as much to him; no ſooner ſaid but it was done, <hi>And Doeg the Edomite turned, fell upon the Prieſts, and ſlew:</hi> Marke it, for though here is a miſerable deſtruction, bodies and garments too rol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in bloud; yet here is comfort to every true Iſraelite: What is that? To ſee a City lye in aſhes, Prieſts and people wallowing in blood? is there comfort in this? No, and yet <hi>God</hi> will bring com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and good out of all this to his Iſrael anon: Now this is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:155295:6"/>that there are but two Actors in this Tragedy, <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite;</hi> only theſe ſpecified by name. True it is we ſhall reade anon in the third Section of <hi>Three thouſand</hi> choſen men out of Iſrael, whom <hi>Saul</hi> called together to guard his perſon, he ſaid, being affraid of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> (as the <hi>Bird</hi> of <hi>Prey</hi> is of the Partridge.) But nothing they did, not a drop of blood ſhed by them; Theſe only are the Active Men, theſe two, skilfull to deſtroy, <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>Edomite.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thanke <hi>God</hi> for this; <hi>Wickedneſſe proceeds from the wicked man.</hi> Iſrael can waſh their hands in the innocency of their hearts, and ſay, They are free touching this matter; for (which will be more cleare anon) Iſrael cannot charge any more, then two amongſt thoſe <hi>three thouſand,</hi> their King, and his <hi>Edomite;</hi> More were guilty of that bloodſhed, that is certaine; for the Edomite was not ſingular, but plurall, as will appeare by and by; but no more could Iſrael charge with the blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that their hands had ſhed it, but <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>Edomite</hi> only. And the charge lay heavy upon <hi>Saul,</hi> like as a heavy burthen unſupportable, as a Milſtone, preſſing him downe upon his owne ſword, and then Lower. He had ſhed blood <hi>to his power,</hi> and blood purſued him, till it had made a more cleane riddance of him, and his houſe, then he made at <hi>Nob,</hi> for there one Prieſt eſcaped his butchers knife; here, not one ſhall eſcape. This we may reade in a Book I have ſeen called the <hi>Kings Chronicle.</hi> And ſo God reckoned with <hi>Saul</hi> to the laſt drop,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sect. p.</hi> 26.27.</note> which he hath ſhed; for <hi>God</hi> has barrelled-up the ſpilt Blood of the Righteous, as he bottles-up their Teares.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> The Prieſts Arraignment, impleadings, and Anſwers run-up pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell with ours in theſe times, ſo does the upſhot or determination of the buſineſſe; for there was Peace in propoſition, but none in conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David.</hi> So here. <hi>Saul</hi> has ſhed blood, which runs-up to theſe times too, but with a fuller ſtream of <hi>bloods:</hi> yet the voice of <hi>Blood</hi> cryes louder, then does the voice of <hi>Bloods.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SO now <hi>Saul</hi> has done execution, and <hi>God</hi> has dealt with <hi>Saul</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as He threatens. When we thinke thereon we have cauſe to ſay, and feel the vertue of what we ſay, <hi>My heart trembleth becauſe of Thee,</hi> and I feare for thy judgements. Before I will relate to theſe Times, I will tell one thing very briefly, which ſhall relate to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and <hi>parallel</hi> it ſelfe. Here has beene a faire and peaceable <hi>parley</hi> betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Abimelech</hi> touching <hi>David.</hi> He impleaded <hi>Abimelech,</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:155295:7"/>and gives him leave to make anſwer; which the Prieſt has done, as we heard, the cleareſt and fulleſt that ever was heard. Was there not a ſweet agreement betwixt them? No, it was never intended. <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> it! as we ſay, Tender propoſitions of Peace betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> while the <hi>Evill ſpirit</hi> is upon <hi>Saul,</hi> and the <hi>Edomite</hi> in <hi>Sauls</hi> Boſom! It is to no purpoſe, <hi>vanity of vanitie's</hi> the greateſt vanity; To wiſh or thinke of an <hi>Accommodation</hi> betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David, rebus ſic ſtantibus,</hi> (that muſt be remembred) the <hi>Evill ſpirit</hi> in his place, and the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite in his, and <hi>Saul</hi> quite out of himſelfe; for ſo it was then. No, you will ſay, Let the Prieſt call-back <hi>David,</hi> take from him the Sword (he ſhould have had an hard pull of it) then give it unto <hi>Saul,</hi> and the matter is ended. No: As ſure as the Sunne did ſhine then, and does ſhine now, ſo ſure it is, That this would not have contented <hi>Saul;</hi> but this would have wonderouſly contented him. If the Prieſt would have called back <hi>David,</hi> demanded the Sword, and, being given into his hand, have ſheathed it into <hi>Davids</hi> Bowels, or have given it <hi>Saul,</hi> that he might doe that horrid execution with his owne hands. Then the Prieſt had been a <hi>Right</hi>-man, for <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervice: Then here had beene Peace betwixt <hi>Saul</hi> and the Prieſt, ſuch as would have pleaſed all three. The <hi>Divel, Saul.</hi> and the <hi>Edomite</hi> too: Then <hi>Saul</hi> would have <hi>bleſſed</hi> the Prieſt <hi>in The Name of the Lord,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thou haſt compaſsion on me.</hi> Doe I ſpeake without the Book? No, it is every word ſacred Truth, you ſhall heare more of it in a fitter place. We muſt ſee now how the lines of this Accuſation put up by <hi>Saul</hi> againſt <hi>Abimelech,</hi> run parallel with the Kings accuſation, ſuggeſted to him by his <hi>vile Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours</hi> againſt his faithfull Servants at this day. The King pleads Law for what he does; ſo did <hi>Saul</hi> too: for he chargeth this heavily upon <hi>Abimelech, That he enquired of the Lord for David;</hi> gave <hi>Bread to Davids mouth, and the ſword into his hand.</hi> All this was againſt the <hi>knowne lawes</hi> of the Land, as <hi>Saul</hi> ſeemes to conceive. Theſe are the Kings charges too, I will ſpeake thereof in order; The firſt Charge is,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That Abimelech enquired of The LORD.</hi> So ſhould <hi>Saul</hi> have done then: and ſo ſhould the King have done now; not hearkning to <hi>vile Councellours, whoſe graves</hi> The <hi>LORD</hi> has made, for <hi>they are vile</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nahum.</hi> 2.44.</note>; hee muſt not adviſe with them, rather <hi>let them flie to the Pit; He that ruleth over men muſt be juſt; ruling in the feare of God</hi>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.3</note>; <hi>Therefore made He thee King over them</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.2.</note>. Wherefore? <hi>To doe judgement and juſtice: He ſhall judge THY People with Righteouſneſſe, and THY Poore with Iudgement.</hi> There is a <hi>muſt</hi> and a <hi>ſhall</hi> for the greateſt King that ever was. It is very em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaticall too, and as notable; <hi>Thy People, Thy Poore;</hi> GODS <hi>People,</hi> and GODS <hi>Poore</hi> muſt be judged with Righteous Judgement. But ſo it cannot be but by <hi>enquiring of The</hi> LORD, <hi>what He ſaith,</hi> taking Counſell from His Mouth, and from His <hi>Law-Booke,</hi> which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:155295:7"/>the King ſtands charged <hi>to write for himſelfe, for it muſt be with him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.18.19.</note> 
                     <hi>and therein be muſt reade all the dayes of his life, that he may learne to feare The LORD <hi>his</hi> GOD, <hi>to keepe all the words of the Law, and the ſtatutes to doe them.</hi> This the <hi>Parliament</hi> doe, They enquire of The <hi>Lord</hi> by prayer, and faſting, They take direction from His Law-book, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually with them, wherein they reade, and whereby they order the great affaires of The Kingdome. Great uſe of a <hi>Law-booke,</hi> and to have it continually with them, before their eyes. And this is all the Crime that can be objected and proved againſt them. <hi>They enquire of The</hi> LORD, and conſult with This Law-booke. It is well they doe; They can thanke God for that. <hi>Sauls</hi> accuſation runs on.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The Prieſt has given David Bread.</hi> The King by his wicked Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell accuſeth his Parliament even ſo; They have given his good Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple bread, that is <hi>life</hi> in our ſenſe, which, by a Figure, we may call <hi>bread.</hi> They have given a poore dead People <hi>life</hi> againe, and <hi>bread</hi> to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine life. They have given (we thanke them heartily) life to their lawes life to their liberties, life to the ſoule of their life, to their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; and this they had not done, but by <hi>enquiring of the</hi> LORD, and doing all by <hi>Statute Law;</hi> and this we call <hi>bread.</hi> There has been ſomething like this bread given to the People, <hi>Shew bread,</hi> rather bread in ſhew, <hi>ſtone</hi> indeed; and ſomething they had given them like a <hi>fiſh,</hi> but indeed a Serpent Now the Kings good People will deſire no more of their King, but that he would give his People <hi>Bread,</hi> bread under this figure which we may call <hi>life;</hi> or bread indeed, and properly ſo called, which more then too cruelly, was and is denyed to <hi>David.</hi> The third charge followes, and that is grievous.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>And a ſword,</hi> ſayes <hi>Saul</hi> then; That ſeemes to be the quarrell now, (and but ſeemes) that the <hi>Sword,</hi> Forts, Caſtles, Townes, Ships, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition of the Kingdome, (all which we underſtand by the <hi>Sword</hi>) is put into <hi>Davids</hi> hand, Truſty, welbeloved, and faithfull: Well, and well indeed, may we poore people ſay, that the Sword is given into <hi>Davids</hi> hand (the Parliaments hand) for they will manage it for our good to defend us, and offend the Philiſtines. The Parliament will not cut our throats, we are very aſſured and confident thereof. But the <hi>Edomite</hi> (wee ſhall know him anon, if wee know him not yet) would have cut our throats, before this time, all their throats that had <hi>their hand with David,</hi> had he had the <hi>Sword</hi> delivered into his hand. We can confide in none but <hi>David:</hi> no wiſe man will blame us, for him we know, a man after <hi>Gods</hi> owne heart; and the <hi>Edomite</hi> we know, and ſhall know him better anon, a <hi>Right</hi> man, for he is the right hand of the Devill. We are glad, that the <hi>Sword</hi> is in <hi>Davids</hi> hand. But yet this was charged againſt the Prieſt then and the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> now, that <hi>David had the ſword.</hi> And what ſhall I ſay to this?
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:155295:8"/>whereunto GOD, <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Law</hi> ſpeakes Reaſon and more, that ſo it ought to be; the Sword ought to be given into <hi>Davids</hi> hand, a faithfull Man, in whom the people may confide. A Man will truſt no other in ſhutting-in the windowes, doores and gates of his houſe: great Reaſon there ſhould be the ſame care had about the great <hi>houſe,</hi> and Truſt of the Kingdome, the frontier-Towns there.</p>
                  <p>But why given out of his Majeſties hand, and given into <hi>Davids</hi> hand?</p>
                  <p>Becauſe the <hi>Sword</hi> was never in the Kings hand, as his proper right there, any more then the <hi>Sword</hi> was in <hi>Sauls</hi> hand, as his proper goods there. Therefore we ſpeake not properly, <hi>given-out.</hi> The <hi>Sword</hi> is Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels Sword, the <hi>Common Truſt</hi> of the Kingdome: belonging, indeed, to the great <hi>Fiduciary</hi> there; and yet is the <hi>Sword</hi> not out of the Kings hands, but given into <hi>Davids</hi> hands, for a ſecond Reaſon.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe, as the <hi>Edomite</hi> was neareſt to <hi>Sauls</hi> hand, and heart too at that time: So the <hi>Papiſt</hi> is ſo neare to the Kings heart now, that he is as deare to him, as he is neare, even as his Right Arme, and Right Eye, <hi>eternally</hi> his, for ought we can gather from his <hi>writ.</hi> I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this with the words of an honeſt Servant to an overbearing Maſter: <q rend="inline">I will ſerve you (Sir) if you wil ſerve The <hi>Lord.</hi>You may command me, when <hi>God</hi> commands you. I will heartily obey your commands, when you ſhall ſo obey <hi>Gods</hi> commands<note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, The head hath an <hi>Head;</hi> All things ſhall be done as you will have it; But you muſt command as <hi>God</hi> will have it. <hi>Ignatius</hi> to a Prieſt <hi>Chryſo.</hi>
                        </note>. I pray you heartily give me leave to be honeſt and faithfull: If you will not, ſo I will be whether you will or no. Doe you what you <hi>will,</hi> I will do what I <hi>ought.</hi>
                     </q> No man can diſlike this, except <hi>Saul,</hi> and his <hi>Edomite;</hi> I need ſay no more in a caſe which is ſo fully opened and cleared, that all the <hi>Malignants</hi> in the world ſhall not be able to darken it to the worlds end. I will not ſay, looke upon Mr. <hi>Pryn's</hi> booke, (I will name him for honour ſake, and to ſpight the Devil) reade him, or chooſe you whether you will or not; we muſt ſay, Bleſſed be God for His ſervant, who has ſtood-up in the gap by the power of His might, and held up His hand for him ever ſince againſt the Mighty, <hi>Bleſſed be God.</hi> But notwithſtanding all this is cleared, to be all <hi>Truth, Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Law,</hi> and more yet, and that is moſt of all, a <hi>Command</hi> for all this, the Parliament has done, from Gods mouth too. Yet ſuch <hi>Evill Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> over-rule the King and the caſe that he does now as <hi>Saul</hi> did then, and much more, kils the Prieſts, and deſtroyes Cities. So far as his Arme can reach he has overthrowne thoſe,<note place="margin">Tunc vere victus quando tot vicis prudentes. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing. Edw. 2. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>5.</hi>
                     </note> whoſe hand is with <hi>David;</hi> therein giving himſelf the greateſt overthrow, for, no ſuch victory againſt the King, as for him to have victory againſt his good people, as was ſaid of <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond overcomming his Parliament once, and deſtroying himſelfe for ever. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> did in his dayes; thus and more the King, ſeduced by Evill Counſell, and acted by evill inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:155295:8"/>does in theſe dayes; as followes, and what <hi>Saul</hi> did firſt. <hi>Saul</hi> was <hi>Davids</hi> Lord on earth, but he hunts after <hi>Davids</hi> ſoule, that hee might not live upon the ground. <hi>Saul</hi> is <hi>Davids</hi> King, and <hi>Davids</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor. The Prieſts King, and the Prieſts murtherer, by the hand of an <hi>Edomite.</hi> Ah <hi>Lord,</hi> who can expreſſe the miſerable plight, and how dolefull the condition is, the <hi>evill ſpirit</hi> has driven <hi>Saul</hi> into! He is Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raels King, and he is ſmiting Iſraels City! The great <hi>Fiduciary</hi> of the Kingdome, and the greateſt Traytor there. This tells us what is done now. <hi>David</hi> is perſecuted now; and his King, ſeduced by Edomites, <hi>Davids</hi> adverſaries, perſecutes him becauſe who ſo <hi>faithfull as he in all the Kingdome!</hi> A defendor of the Faith, and, by <hi>his evill Counſell,</hi> a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of the Faith. A maintainer of the Goſpel in profeſſion, and a perſecutor of the faithfull Miniſters publiſhers of the ſame, the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of the Church and the glory of Chriſt.</hi> The great <hi>Fiduciary</hi> of the Kingdome, yet, ſeduced by an <hi>evill Councell,</hi> he betrayes that great Truſt. Englands King, and Englands deſtroyer; The Lord of their Cities, and waſter of the ſame. Are not theſe grievous words? Yes, they muſt be ſo, plaine Truth, direct and home; what expectation of any good, but from ſuch-like-words. If ever the King come to himſelfe, finde himſelfe <hi>loſt,</hi> (for murtherers have ſtolne him away) then ſuch words as theſe will be to his heart, and may ſerve to uſher-in <hi>Pardon,</hi> peace, and comfort: for the <hi>ſowrer the herbes, the ſweeter the Paſſeover:</hi> whereas pleaſing words from <hi>vile</hi> flatterers, his Court Chaplaines, have wounded their Maſter, and left him more then halfe dead. Such words as theſe may kill him out-right, and, by <hi>Gods</hi> grace quicken him againe to a <hi>life</hi> indeed. I am glad I have ſpoken; for firſt, I have ſaid no more, but what is already told in <hi>Gath,</hi> and <hi>publiſhed in the ſtreets of Aſchalon.</hi> Secondly, what if it were not told by me, nor as aforeſaid, yet all created ſtrength cannot ſtop the mouth of <hi>blouds,</hi> ſo loud it cries; Irelands bloud, what an Ocean of bloud is there? Cyciters bloud; Burminghams bloud; Banburies bloud, (ſhedding of this bloud, was counted a <hi>fine</hi> device, as Briſtols bloud intended to be ſhed) Oxfords bloud; Bloud here, and there, and everywhere, whereto the hand could reach; O what a voice is here, as the voice of many waters; or, Thunders! Is there a voice that can out-cry, I meane, cry louder to Heaven, and in the Eares of the <hi>Lord,</hi> then can the voice of blouds? yes the voice of bloud, cries louder then the <hi>bloud of Abel,</hi> or the blouds ſhed from righteous <hi>Abel</hi> unto this day; and there is the hope of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael concerning their King; The voice <hi>of the bloud of ſprinkling,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.24.</note> 
                     <hi>that ſpeakes better things</hi> then that of <hi>Abel; Better things;</hi> that cryed from the earth for a curſe upon the earth, and <hi>Cain</hi> there:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.12.</note> This cries in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for mercy to ſuch ſinners on earth, who can ſay, not with <hi>Cain,</hi> My <hi>puniſhment,</hi> but, my ſin is greater then I can beare, yet not too great
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:155295:9"/>for Chriſt to beare, a <hi>Redeemer</hi> that is ſtrong, a <hi>Saviour</hi> to the <hi>utmoſt;</hi> There is hope in Iſrael concerning that. And here is ground of hope too, becauſe theſe <hi>Stephens,</hi> the ſlain all the day long, can pray for their King all the day long, crying with a loud voice, not more for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at ſuch a time, then for their King, ſaying, <hi>Lord lay not this ſinne to our Kings charge. Amen. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> Quaeries touching the Edomite, whether by the <hi>knowne Lawes</hi> of Iſraels Kingdome, <hi>Saul</hi> might entertaine him in his Court; grant him a Commiſſion to ſmite a City of Prieſts; whether any reaſon for that; whether ſingle or plurall; and whether by any poſſible meanes an Edomite may be made ſerviceable to Iſrael; How it relates to the preſent, exemplifying the Hiſtory of our Time.</head>
                  <p>VVHy does <hi>King Saul</hi> take an <hi>Edomite</hi> into his Court,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note> to be an Officer there?</p>
                  <p>It is anſwered in effect before;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Saul</hi> is King and he knew himſelfe ſo to be,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note> and will chuſe his owne Officers; may he not?</p>
                  <p>No indeed,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> he may not unleſſe it be to be his <hi>Heardſman,</hi> and there ſhould be caution, and ſome conſultation about that too. Queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he muſt not chuſe a ſervant to be chiefe in his houſe; to tranſact the great affaires of his Kingdome there, without the allowance and conſent of <hi>All Iſrael,</hi> becauſe <hi>Saul</hi> does not chuſe for himſelfe, but for the whole Kingdome.</p>
                  <p>But it is written,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ob.</note> 
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt not abhor an Edomite.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yes,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> that is moſt true; it is the charge of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and we have the Reaſon;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.8.</note> 
                     <hi>For he is thy brother: Nor ſhalt thou ab or an Egyptian, becauſe thou waſt a ſtranger in his land.</hi> What is the meaning of this? This; <hi>we muſt not be unnaturall:</hi> nor <hi>muſt we forget old favours.</hi> But it does not follow from hence, I hope, that therefore <hi>Saul</hi> might take an Edomite, make him a Chiefe Ruler in his houſe; or that, he might put conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in an Egyptian; for the charge is contrary. And if <hi>Saul</hi> will entertaine an intimacy, and familiarity with an Edomite an old ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary to Iſrael, (as we have heard and ſeene, and ſhall make it more legible yet) It does plainly argue,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Sect.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Saul</hi> to be no true friend to Iſrael. <hi>Sauls</hi> heart cannot be upright toward <hi>Iſrael, when it cleaves to Iſraels ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary in love:</hi> He cannot heartily deſire the peace of Iſrael, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily love an enemy to that peace. I pray let us aske ſome more que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions touching the Edomite; I will anſwer by the <hi>Booke,</hi> then good Law and Reaſon both.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:155295:9"/>
                  <p>Why did <hi>Saul</hi> make the Edomite Generall in this warre againſt <hi>David?</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> gives ſomeanſwer to that, with a little Reaſon,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> 
                     <hi>Becauſe his ſonne Ionathan ſtirred-up David to lye in wait for Saul as at this day.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.8.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>As at this day indeed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note> But this anſwer makes us more unreſolved then before; for all the world knowes, that <hi>Ionathan</hi> was a good man; and <hi>David</hi> as good as he; beſides, we finde <hi>David</hi> fleeing away from the face of <hi>Saul</hi> like a Partridge; and <hi>Saul</hi> hunting him like a Dog. Let us heare Reaſon, I pray you. Was it not, That the Edomite might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the <hi>ſword</hi> our of <hi>Davids</hi> hand?</p>
                  <p>No, no, that could not be it;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> for when <hi>Saul</hi> ſpeakes out his minde freely, as ſometimes he did, (for a wicked heart will diſcover it ſelfe) amongſt his Servants; he does not bid them, fetch the <hi>ſword</hi> from <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> but kill him: <hi>And Saul ſpake to Ionathan, and to all his ſervants,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.1.</note> 
                     <hi>that they ſhould kill David.</hi> It is <hi>Davids life,</hi> not the <hi>ſword,</hi> that is aimed at. And the <hi>Edomite</hi> was a <hi>Right</hi> man for that ſervice, for he was a <hi>mighty man,</hi> mighty to <hi>do miſchiefe,</hi> and skilfull to deſtroy; Whom? <hi>David,</hi> and All them that had an hand with <hi>David.</hi> That is the direct An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Saul</hi> indeed ſpake merrily to the people as he went along by the way, and would make them beleeve, that he had taken the <hi>Edomite</hi> to his ſide, and ſealed him a Commiſſion, becauſe <hi>he is affraid of David;</hi> he tells them more then twice, <hi>David lay in wait to kill him;</hi> therefore he tooke the Edomite to his ſide; for, who ſo faithfull as he to defend his maſter from <hi>Davids</hi> violence! (a poor-hunted Partridge:) or a more <hi>Right,</hi> handed man to execute his maſters command againſt <hi>David?</hi> True it was, <hi>David</hi> never durſt ſtand to it, till hee came to <hi>Keilah,</hi> and there, had not the Inhabitants proved themſelves ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and treacherous— he had guarded himſelfe and fenced his throat, and hazarded <hi>Sauls.</hi> But <hi>Saul</hi> feared <hi>David</hi> no more, then the Birds of Prey a hunted Partridge, (that is the expreſſion;) And <hi>kill David,</hi> that was his charge. There is one doubt more, and occaſions another queſtion.</p>
                  <p>Was this <hi>Edomite</hi> ſingular or plurall?<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſingular number ſure. <hi>Doeg</hi> was but one. But let us note,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> that <hi>One</hi> is mentioned ſometimes, not to exclude a <hi>ſecond,</hi> but to imply the firſt, chiefeſt in place; and ſo more <hi>mighty,</hi> and principall then the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, becauſe of his place; as <hi>Iehoram</hi> is ſaid to <hi>compell Iudah to commit fornication.</hi> When <hi>Athaliah</hi> was as maſculine, and imperious, yea as miſchievous that way, and yet not named in that verſe, becauſe ſhee acted by power from her husband, not ſo cleare to every mans eye: And ſo <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite is mentioned ſingle, as if he did all, becauſe the chiefeſt in favour with his King. The meaning of the queſtion then is, Was there but one Edomite imployed in that war, or were there more?</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:155295:10"/>
                  <p>There were more ſure;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> for it is not imaginable, that <hi>Doeg</hi> alone could deſtroy the City of Prieſts, men, women and children there; doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there were more Edomites there, or baſtard Iſraelites, as <hi>Right</hi>-men for <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervice (as the word is, if men can be <hi>Right,</hi> who are the ſeed of the <hi>Crooked Serpent</hi>) as <hi>Doeg</hi> was; Nay it is probable there were many in <hi>Sauls</hi> Camp <hi>Right</hi>-men, Edomites I meane, of that genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: for thus it is; When a <hi>Doeg</hi> is entertained at Court, is favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red there, he will work for his Country-men what he can and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his power, that they may have place, and reſpect thereabouts that they may be of uſe and ſervice, when the King ſhall riſe-up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>David.</hi> One queſtion more, with a reſolution, touching the Edomite.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saul</hi> his maſter has entertained him:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note> Is there no meanes to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, whereby he may be made a faithfull ſervant to Iſrael?</p>
                  <p>No,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> by no meanes.</p>
                  <p>What!<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note> not poſſible to make him a <hi>Right-man?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>No,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> not to Iſrael; but to <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervice he will be right and ſtraight.</p>
                  <p>Me thinkes Iſrael might have dealt with him,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note> as we with Papiſts, bring him to Church; might they not have done ſo?</p>
                  <p>Yes;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> and to no purpoſe at all; for he will goe <hi>to the houſe of Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech himſelfe,</hi> (that is, to the Church, as we too commonly call it) and a miſchievous perſon though he be, yet he will ſit there cloſe to his ſolemne ſervice, and pretend there, <hi>he has a vow upon him;</hi> you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not worke upon him that way, to make him <hi>Right</hi> for Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>Then try him another way;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note> give him, as we to the Papiſts, the <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegeance; ſweare him faithfull to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>King;</hi> an Oath is a ſacred band, that will binde him to Iſrael ſure, will it not? an <hi>Oath</hi> I meane, ſuch a ſacred <hi>Band?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hang him:<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> for like the poſſeſſed man, no <hi>Bands</hi> will hold him; he will breake all <hi>Cords,</hi> ſuch a childe of Belial is he, except one, and that the <hi>Hangman</hi> muſt pluck-up-cloſe to his neck, then turne him downe, for by no meanes can you make an <hi>Edomite</hi> ſtand right to Iſrael.</p>
                  <p>This is very ſutable to the time; But for the firſt Queſtions: <hi>How farre the Kings power reacheth for the choice of his owne Miniſters,</hi> I leave, as in manners I ought, to the determination of the High Court, which is this, <hi>That the King muſt chooſe ſuch Miniſters as his good people may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in: and by no meanes ſuch, who are ſworne enemies to the peace of the King, and proſperity of the Kingdome.</hi> A mans private judgement may be <hi>ſteeped</hi> in his <hi>affections:</hi> he may cleave more in love to a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, then to a whole Kingdome; and in choice of perſons to places, he may ſtand byaſſed to his owne <hi>will</hi> and ends, which All Iſrael, a <hi>Parliament</hi> there, cannot doe. Therefore it is againſt the <hi>knowne lawes</hi> of Iſraels Kingdome, That Iſraels King ſhould, by himſelf alone, make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:155295:10"/>choice of Perſons to high place there, for it is againſt the SU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PREME LAW, the <hi>welfare of the People:</hi> And <hi>Saul,</hi> taking that liberty againſt that <hi>knowne Law,</hi> had deſtroyed the Cities of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and had ſlaine <hi>David</hi> too, had not the <hi>Lord</hi> interpoſed His Almighty Arme.</p>
                  <p>To the other, which I ſhould not make a queſtion, <hi>whether by any meanes a Papiſt, may be made ſerviceable to Iſrael?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is Anſwered as before; <hi>by no meanes,</hi> which man can uſe: You cannot change the <hi>Ethiopians Skin,</hi> not the <hi>Leopards ſpots.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 13.23.</note> He will goe to Church as the Edomite to <hi>Abimilechs Houſe,</hi> and yet be <hi>mighty to doe miſchiefe:</hi> You may ſweare him to the King and Kingdome: Bind him with that <hi>Sacred Band,</hi> he will bee willingly bound, for he was a reſervation; Or if you preſſe him hard, hee is informed very well, <hi>That he cannot be bound to Heretickes,</hi> (as he cals them) in <hi>any bands;</hi> you may put bands upon him, he will beake them as eaſily, as you can breake <hi>burnt Flaxe.</hi> The Doctrine of his Church and her Lawes (written in blood) doe abſolve, and ſet free This <hi>Child of Belial,</hi> from all bandsand at liberty to doe all manner of miſchiefe. And ſo he has done, and it is the very purpoſe of his heart to doe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Power in his hand. All the miſchiefe as his manner is, to Iſrael, being the fruitfull Parent of all the Rebellions, Treaſons, Maſſacres, (and ſo forth, for there is no end) That have beene acted thorow the Chriſtian World, as <hi>at this day.</hi> You may then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them Traytors, to the Peace and Crowne of the King and Kingdome: for ſo is every Papiſt, (ſaid a great States man in our Kingdom) holding to the Tenets of the Romiſh Church; <hi>Traytors in hand, or in heart; in action, or affection.</hi> And ſo ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> of himſelf (once an <hi>Aug. Moncke</hi>) and of all his fraternity, or Brother-hood there <q rend="inline">
                        <hi>Wee are all Men of Blood,</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Nemo noſtrum non erat vir ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinum, ſi non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pete tamen corde Abhorrebam vel ipſum Nomen. <hi>W. Hus in Galas. Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</note> ſayes hee wee hate a true Proteſtant (ſuch an one as <hi>Iohn Huſſ</hi>) with our heart, and we will preſecute him with our hand, to the death. We abhorretheir very Name: we would not have a man of that profeſſion to live upon the Earth;</q> ſo ſaid <hi>Luther</hi> having his eyes ſhut up, and living in <hi>Monkery.</hi> Why then, when they are declared to bee ſo, So Rebellious to the Lawes of the <hi>King</hi> of Heaven: So Trayterous to the <hi>Crowne</hi> of the King and Kingdome: Let it bee done unto him according to the Judgement of our Law, The Hangman muſt doe his Office: ſee what that cord will doe.</p>
                  <p>To the other Queſtions, <hi>Wherefore the King taketh the Edomites, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, and Papiſts</hi> (Davids Enemies) all To his ſide? Why his heart cleaveth to ſuch Enemies as theſe in love? His Anſwer is (adviſing with pernicious Counſellors, in whoſe hand he is) as <hi>Sauls</hi> was, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is perſwaded <hi>Theſe are Men faithfull to his Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:155295:11"/>his Service (ſo they are indeed) and will defend him from <hi>David,</hi> who (as he ſeems to ſay) <hi>lyes in wait for him, as it is at this day:</hi> and as <hi>David</hi> lay in wait for <hi>Saul</hi> in thoſe dayes. So we may mocke men, but <hi>God</hi> will not be mocked. It were endleſſe, and needleſſe, to tell ſtories, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this matter, how <hi>Right</hi>-handed-men Papiſts have beene to their Kings, and their Kingdomes in all Ages. Thank Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> (I will name him againe being reſolved to anger the Divell, and all his Biſhops) he has told us enough, and abundantly ſatisfied us at this point. I proceed; <hi>Saul</hi> may ſay, <hi>David lay in wait to take away his life,</hi> therefore he tooke the <hi>Edomite</hi> to his ſide, to defend him from <hi>Davids</hi> ſword; when the truth was, <hi>Saul</hi> perſecuted <hi>David thorough the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of Iſrael:</hi> and that he might doe to <hi>David</hi> according to all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <hi>of his ſoule,</hi> he tooke the <hi>Edomite</hi> to his ſide, a Mighty Adverſary to Iſrael and as Skilfull to deſtroy.</p>
                  <p>The very ſame Reaſon, and no other now, wherefore the King (in the hands of bloudy, and pernicious Adverſaries) takes Atheiſts, and Papiſts to him now, why he cleaves to them in love? Becauſe they are mighty to doe miſchiefe, skilfull to ſhed bloud, as is legible now in Ireland and England both.</p>
                  <p>But this we muſt note; Though <hi>Sauls</hi> excuſe for taking to himſelfe ſuch a <hi>guard,</hi> and ſuch a Captaine over them, was not ſo ſpecious, as it was ridiculous; yet there was <hi>bloodſhed</hi> in good earneſt, which was charged heavily upon <hi>Saul,</hi> for it ruined him and all <hi>his houſe,</hi> and <hi>all together,</hi> as we reade. We muſt apply this now, and approve our ſelves faithfull to the Soul of our King, That his Conſcience may ſpeak-out before it be too late, and he ſpeechleſſe, (then commonly the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſpeakes loudeſt.) That the Conſcience may ſpeak-out, and in ſeaſon, we apply and reade on; So will the bloud-ſhed in Ireland, and England by the <hi>Edomites</hi> in both places, bee charged upon the King, whoſe ſervants they are, and whoſe Commiſſion they have, (ſuch a pernicious Counſell he has;) <hi>Turne thou and fall upon the Prieſt, and people all, whoſe hand is with David: and the Edomite turned, &amp;c.</hi> This is the <hi>Edomites</hi> Commiſſion now againſt all that have an hand with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid;</hi> And therefore all the Bloud they have ſhed there or here, ſhall be charged upon the <hi>King.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not the bloud of <hi>Ireland</hi> ſure,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ob.</note> not a drop.</p>
                  <p>Yes every drop,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> though it be an <hi>Occan</hi> a.</p>
                  <p>He called them Rebels,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Ob.</note> and cauſed them to be proclaimed ſo in forty Papers at leaſt; and Rebels with an <hi>accent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We remember ſome ſuch matter,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> and as it harpened, ſaw the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation; but it was not hearty; if ſo, then not onely the <hi>Publique Cryer,</hi> but every Poſt and Pillar, had proclaimed them <hi>Rebels,</hi> for ſo the Kings beſt Subjects were proclaimed the yeare before: We un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand<note n="a" place="margin">The bloud, a Ruler commands to be ſhed, or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to be ſhed, The <hi>Lord</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth upon the Rulers ſcore. <hi>Thou haſt killed.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.9. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.19.</note>
                     <pb facs="tcp:155295:11"/>well when a thing is done <hi>heartily,</hi> for then the whole Land ſhall ring of it; every City and Towne there, every Church and Chappell: nor ſo onely, <hi>Stockes</hi> and <hi>Stones</hi> ſhall be taught to ſpeake, and to proclaime <hi>Rebels:</hi> ſo good Subjects were proclaimed <hi>Rebels;</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels indeed, as thoſe in Ireland, not ſo proclaimed, but coldly and faintly, <hi>God</hi> He knowes.</p>
                  <p>His Majeſty made offer to goe himſelfe and fight with the Rebels,<note place="margin">B.</note> his ſtomack did ſo riſe againſt them.</p>
                  <p>We remember his <hi>Secretary</hi> wrote ſome ſuch matter;<note place="margin">A.</note> but the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary</hi> knew, the ſtomack of his wicked <hi>Counſell</hi> roſe againſt <hi>Hull,</hi> and was cager upon that place to take the Ammunition thence, which they would have had firſt, and have gone to ſuppreſſe the <hi>Rebels</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; we remember this very well.</p>
                  <p>And his Majeſty ſayes, <hi>his ſoule bleedeth over the bloudſhed in Ireland.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">B.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>We doe not certainly know what his Majeſty ſayes,<note place="margin">A.</note> for we cannot thinke that we reade his words. His Secretary has told us ſo much, and truly I can forbeare him no longer; he is one of the vileſt <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites</hi> in all the world: one of the <hi>vile Counſellours</hi> ſure, who perſwaded the King to intercept the proviſion of Cloathes, and other things ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding over to a poore, peeled, naked people; and then would make us beleeve, They pirty the peoples nakedneſſe, and their ſoules bleed over their miſery. The Kings party make all ſupplyes over to the Rebels there, to make them the more able for the ſhedding of more bloud, and then tells us, <hi>The Kings heart bleeds over the bloodſhed there.</hi> They call them Rebels there, and call them over hither to do the like execution here; and here they doe it with all their might; and yet the <hi>Secretary</hi> tels us <hi>The Kings ſoule bleeds over this bloudſhed.</hi> O helliſh blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy; horrible hypocriſie!</p>
                  <p>If the Secretaries bloud, and all the bloud, that runnes in the veins of that Helliſh Counſell about his Majeſty, were ſhed, it would not redeeme the wrong they have done to the King their Maſter, I doe not adde, and the Kindome, by theſe notorious Blaſphemies, Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions. Remonſtrances, and <hi>Contra-Remonſtrances;</hi> declaring one thing with the Tongue, and then the contrary with the Hand; ſo making us beleeve, That the King their Maſter is <hi>as one of them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Obeb.</hi> 11.</note> (which we tremble to think-of,) as notorious an Hypocrite as was he, wee have often read of, and we have never read the like <hi>till this day,</hi> whoſe foot ſtood in the <hi>path of the deſtroyer,</hi> did drive-on furiouſly there, <hi>weeping all along as he went;</hi> (That is the expreſſion,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jer.</hi> 41.6.</note>) as if his ſoule had bled over the bodies, which he had ſlaine: when yet he went-on fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly reſolved to ſlay more; and ſo many he had ſlaine, that he has filled a great <hi>Pit with the ſlame.</hi> GOD beholds all this and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it. Rebels in Ireland, howſoever proclaimed againſt for faſhion
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:155295:12"/>ſake are the Kings good Subjects here, helping on the Deſigne: And they, who oppoſed their Bloody Deſignes here and there, not in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne onely, but in execution, are called <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Rebells</hi> both and all heartily. Here is a double Iniquity. We do not pray for, we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precat againſt the Judgement, but the <hi>Lord lookes</hi> upon this and <hi>will Require it:</hi> He will not indure, to have <hi>evill</hi> cal'd <hi>good,</hi> and good evill. <hi>For three tranſgreſsions of Edom,</hi> &amp;c. But of that anon. So much for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to the <hi>Queries</hi> touching the Edomite, his taking into the Court, Deſigning unto Office there, The granting him a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to deſtroy <hi>Neb;</hi> Now, ſee wee how ſtoutly and with what a good will he performed it; <hi>Sauls</hi> Command was to the Edomites heart, and heartily he executes it; So <hi>Saul</hi> ſhall ſee That the Edomite is a <hi>Right</hi> Man,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.17.18.</note> no ſooner Saul had ſaid, <hi>Turne and ſlay the Prieſts of the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their hand alſo was with</hi> David, <hi>and they knew when he fled and did not ſhew it me;</hi> No ſooner this was ſpoken to the <hi>Edomite,</hi> but <hi>he turned and</hi> did accordingly: he <hi>fell upon the Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>ſlew,</hi> and <hi>ſhewed no pitty. Then Men did groane out of the City, and the Soule of the wounded Cryed-out: Yet</hi> GOD <hi>layeth not</hi> folly to theſe murtherers, <hi>Though they are</hi> of thoſe, <hi>that Rebell againſt the light,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob</hi> 24.12, 13.</note> ſaies <hi>Iob,</hi> offended at thoſe very things our eyes behold at this Day: The <hi>Lord,</hi> who cleares His Servants Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, as the Morning, will cleare His owne Righteouſneſſe as the Noone Day; And though we are but dim-ſighted, yet we ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern it anon I will ſhut up this Chapter, as <hi>David</hi> begins his Pſalme; <hi>Why boaſteſt thou thy ſelfe in miſchiefe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52.1.</note> 
                     <hi>O Mighty Man? The goodneſſe of</hi> God <hi>endureth Continually.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Sad Caſes examined and tryed before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and reſolved from His Mouth; which may ſilence a Poore People, ſlaine all the day long by the <hi>hurtfull</hi> and <hi>oppreſsing</hi> Sword, now in the hand of bloody Edomites.</head>
                  <p>NOw here is a caſe to be tryed before the <hi>Lord</hi> touching theſe ſlain Prieſts, and their deſtroyed City, which, I hope, will give us good ſatisfaction at leaſt ſilence us, when our ſpirits are ſtirred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us beholding the villanous Butcheries the notorious violences ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by our <hi>Turks</hi> (I never yetcal'd them <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> &amp; never will by that Gentile Name in our Land upon our <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and good People (all that have their hand with <hi>David</hi>) &amp; our ſo waſted Towns, and Cities. Touching the <hi>Prieſts</hi> firſt.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:155295:12"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God is Righteous,</hi> ſo we have concluded,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.13.14.</note> yet the Righteous ſay now as once they did: <hi>Wherefore lookeſt Thou upon them that deale treacherouſly, and holdeſt Thy Tongue, when the wicked devoureth the Man that is more Righteous then hee? And makeſt men as the Fiſhes of the Sea, as the Creeping things, that have no Ruler over them?</hi> Nay, they ſpeake now almoſt as fooliſhly as once they did, <hi>it is in vaine to ſerve</hi> GOD, <hi>and what profit is it, that we have kept the Ordinances?</hi> The <hi>Proud are happy, for</hi> they <hi>that tempt</hi> GOD <hi>are ſet up,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.13, 14.</note> 
                     <hi>while they that ſerve Him truely are caſt downe and deſtroyed:</hi> This was <hi>Abimilechs</hi> Caſe; he has done his duty, the <hi>Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite</hi> himſelfe being witneſſe, by direction from <hi>Gods</hi> Mouth, for hee <hi>enquired of the</hi> LORD for <hi>David,</hi> &amp;c. Yet he is cut off from the Earth with, 84. more, the Prieſts of The <hi>Lord,</hi> as not ſit to live upon the ground. So the Prieſts were dealt with then, and ſo now, So Cruelly. And what then? Yet the <hi>Potſheards</hi> muſt not ſtrive with their Maker; but if they will ſtrive (the Servants of The LORD, <hi>muſt not ſtrive,</hi> but if they will ſtrive) then with the worke of their owne hands, the <hi>Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheards, with the Potſheards of the Earth.</hi> The LORD is <hi>Righteous,</hi> and His Judgements as the great deep. The Glory of His <hi>worke,</hi> even of His <hi>Strange worke,</hi> exceeds infinitely the glory of the Sunne, which yet we cannot pry into; and doth ever ſhine cleare, though ſometimes we ſee it not, and the blind man never. The Cauſe of His Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may be ſecret, but ever Juſt. So we have Concluded. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would cleare the Sad Condition of our good Miniſters now I ſay. 2. There be Sinnes in theſe <hi>Beſt</hi> Miniſters (for none other are perſecuted) and though but little Sins in Compariſon of others of their Tribe (<hi>Great</hi> and Mighty Sinners before The <hi>Lord,</hi> for Men ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the offering of the <hi>Lord</hi> for their Sakes) yet are they Sinnes, and the greater in them becauſe they are indeed the Meſſengers of the Churches, and the glory of Chriſt (The more Glory, The Lord puts upon them, The greater their Sinne) And theſe Sinnes muſt be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in them <hi>by Fire.</hi> But Bleſſed be <hi>God;</hi> That wheras He might have puniſhed them For their Evill doings. hee makes them ſuffer from the hands of wicked men <hi>for Righteouſneſſe ſake;</hi> and ſo honours them with the Glory of Martyrdome, as it is at this day: for doubtleſſe The Miniſters now ſuffer for the Cauſe of Chriſt, if ever any ſuffered for his Cauſe ſince the beginning of the VVorld.</p>
                  <p>But why were the 84. Prieſts ſlaine at the ſame Time? As for <hi>Abimilech</hi> hee might Tranſgreſſe, as a Man: and yet that cannot bee granted in this Caſe, for hee <hi>enquired of the LORD,</hi> did all by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, from His Mouth: hee could call <hi>God</hi> to Record upon his Soule, that he did, what he did, by <hi>Statute-law,</hi> the knowne Law of the Kingdome. But yet ſuppoſe, That <hi>Abimilech</hi> did Tranſgreſſe in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:155295:13"/>giving forth the <hi>ſword,</hi> yet why were the foureſcore and foure Prieſts ſlaine?</p>
                  <p>It is not poſſible for man to ſpeake Reaſon here;<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> though, indeed, there is ſome reaſon given in the Text, the ſame, and as good reaſon as is given now, <hi>becauſe their hands alſo is with David:</hi> Speak Reaſon; and ſpeake out; with whom ſhould ſhe Prieſts be but with <hi>David,</hi> who had wrought ſuch ſalvation for Iſrael? and upon whom, next to <hi>God,</hi> Iſrael had rouled themſelves, and all their concernments? yet this was the reaſon then, and this is all the reaſon now of this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible <hi>perſecution, becauſe their hand is with David (the Worthies, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the Lord there,)</hi> therefore deſtroy the Prieſts, becauſe their <hi>hand is with David;</hi> thus we ſee man can give no reaſon, only <hi>God</hi> can, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; And wee muſt note ſtill, That theſe were cut off with the Sword of an <hi>Edomite,</hi> not becauſe they were greater ſinners then any other Prieſts were, but becauſe they were godly and conſcientious of their duty, that enrageth the <hi>Edomite</hi> againſt them. There is another reaſon alſo which The <hi>Lord</hi> giveth, That other Prieſts might be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby; For note we, the greateſt ſinners are not the greateſt ſufferers in this life, I meane, they have not the greateſt afflictions. Nay, it is moſt commonly cleane contrary, they have no changes in their life; when as the <hi>godly</hi> have changes of ſorrowes.</p>
                  <p>True it is, and we will not make it a queſtion, <hi>Deſtruction is to the wicked, and a ſtrange puniſhment to the workers of iniquity.</hi> But wee muſt note, That to be ſlaine with the ſword of an <hi>Edomite,</hi> is no <hi>ſtrange</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; but the lot of the righteous, their lot to be ſmitten with the hand of violence, and made the <hi>portion of Foxes.</hi> It is ſo, and the will of The <hi>Lord,</hi> it ſhould be ſo, for note we; where the <hi>Lord</hi> gives Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Sword to goe forth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9.5.</note> 
                     <hi>ſpare and pitty none, neither old nor young; neither man nor woman:</hi> He does ſay, <hi>Come not neare any man upon whom is the marke,</hi> (i. e.) to hurt them) He does not ſay, <hi>Come not neare My Sanctuaries,</hi> the Prieſts, or their Cities; The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> chargeth the Sword to beginne there; <hi>And begin at my Sanctuary.</hi> We cannot be ignorant, what the uſe is, the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> would have Prieſts, and people,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet</hi> 4.17.18.19.</note> good and bad make hereof: <hi>If judgement muſt begin at the houſe of</hi> GOD, <hi>what ſhall the end bee of them, that obey not the Goſpell of God? And if the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungodly appeare?</hi> It ſtrikes terrour to the wicked, but ſtrong conſolation to the godly; <hi>Wherefore let them that ſuffer, according to the will of God, commit their ſoules to Him in well doing, as unto A Faithfull Creator.</hi> But with them and their houſe, the <hi>Sword</hi> begins; for note we, who is the Butt of the <hi>Edomites</hi> malice<note n="b" place="margin">Si fuerit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limis fit deſpica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis, &amp;c. Si bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt quiſpiam quaſi m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lus ſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitar. Si malns eſt quaſi bonus honorat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r. <hi>Salv.</hi> li. 4. p. 113.</note> againſt whom then and now, he drawes his Arrow with all his ſtrength? It is that he may ſhoot at and kill the upright in heart; The Prieſts of The <hi>Lord then,</hi> the ſervants of The <hi>Lord</hi> now. Is there
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:155295:13"/>any one, whoſe <hi>hand is with David?</hi> any one, who feares <hi>God</hi> above many? any one, who, as his <hi>Lord and Maſter,</hi> loveth <hi>Righteouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>hateth Iniquity?</hi> Is he ſuch an one? beat him, ſtone him, ſlay him, hang-him; he is <hi>a deg,</hi> uſe him like a Dog; the Parliaments Dog, <hi>his hand is with David,</hi> that is Reaſon enough with an <hi>Edomite,</hi> turne about and ſtay him, for he is no friend to Caeſar. Bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> That this man can <hi>count his coſt,</hi> and account the <hi>reproach of Chriſt great riches.</hi> And bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> that, according to their ſufferings ſhall their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations be, full meaſure, preſſing downe, and running over; he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members his maſters words, <hi>in the world tribulation;</hi> What more? that which makes amends for all, <hi>in Me peace,</hi> that's enough,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.33.</note> But let me aske theſe <hi>Edomites</hi> this queſtion; Have they a <hi>Warrant</hi> for what they doe? Yes, they will ſay, they have a <hi>Commiſsion</hi> from the King under the Great Seale of England, [An honeſt man is the <hi>KEEPER</hi> the while,] which runnes evermore thus, <hi>For the doing of theſe [notorious violences] this commiſsion ſhall be to you, and them, and every one of them, a ſufficient warrant.</hi> But O that they could remember, That <hi>God</hi> is an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger of theſe things; and when He makes <hi>Inquiſition for bloud,</hi> then he that granted this Commiſſion, and hee that executed it,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.14.</note> ſhall fall both together; <hi>Their heart cannot endure, nor can their hands bee ſtrong in the day The</hi> LORD <hi>ſhall deale with them;</hi> and with the KEEPER too, who hath wickedly betrayed the great truſt of the Kingdome. Come we now to the people.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>The children and ſucklings there,</hi> they were ſlaine. The Edomite has made the like ſlaughter in our dayes, for he has ſlaine the mother and the childe together, I thinke the childe in the mothers wombe: We need ſay very little more unto it then this, The Sword was in the <hi>Edomites</hi> hand then; it is in his hand now, (the <hi>Papiſt</hi> I meane ſtill) as bloudy now and ever, as the <hi>Edomite</hi> ever was, and what hee was you ſhall heare anon.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We muſt ſay The LORD is <hi>righteous,</hi> and theſe <hi>ſucklings</hi> had finned, though not after the ſimilitude of <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſſion. Indeed it is a ſad ſight, but we may ſhut the eye, yet ſee into this caſe as farre with our eye ſhut as open; for truly, now we are in the darke, wee are come to the ſecrets of GODS Decree, and there we leave theſe <hi>Sucklings</hi> and Children all. Only I will tell my thoughts, which have ground from holy Scripture; That Parents now, ſeeing their <hi>Sucklings</hi> ſnatched from their breaſts, and their children from out of their deare armes, and from under their wings, becauſe the Parents <hi>have an hand with David,</hi> (pray marke that) may take more comfort in ſuch a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death, theirs or their childrens then if they had ſeen them dye on their bed: For I doe aſſure you, That I have read of ſome Parents, who have beene very ambitious of ſuch a Martyrdome: Oh! to have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:155295:14"/>an hand with <hi>David</hi> to help him againſt the mighty, and an heart with Chriſt and to ſuffer for this, and ſo it is at this Day, is a glorious kind of Martyrdome that it is:</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The People are deſtroyed Men and Women there.<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſw:</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will Anſwer againe, The <hi>Edomite</hi> did it, a ſworne Enemy to Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, as we have read once and againe; he did it, who does thirſt after Bloud; and yet not he alone, It cannot bee reaſonably conceived That he alone, a ſingle man could act ſuch an horrid execution, but helped and ſtrengthned with <hi>Sauls</hi> bloudy Courtiers ſome more of that generation; or <hi>Baſtard</hi> Iſraelites, as Cruell as the Edomite was every whit; And let me ſay too, for it muſt be obſerved, <hi>ſtrengthened</hi> alſo with the Peoples Sinnes, I meane the Sinues of that City. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants there did doubtleſſe <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> the Edomite, and the Baſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Iſraelites againſt their City and their ſelves:<note place="margin">Noſtris peccatis Barbar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fortes ſunt; noſtris vitijs Romanus ſuperat exercitus, <hi>Hiero. Epiſt. l.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Iſid. Peluſ. Ep. l.</hi> 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 294, <hi>p.</hi> 66.</note> (<hi>a</hi>) The Peoples ſins made the <hi>Edomite</hi> ſtrong (we Include all <hi>Davids</hi> Enemies under that Name) againſt the People of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Doubtleſſe it was ſo, for I Read the like expreſſion full for our Inſtruction, The Sinnes of Iſrael ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Eglon</hi>
                     <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.14.</note> againſt Iſrael; Marke it, <hi>Eglon</hi> then and the <hi>Edomite</hi> now had <hi>a Will</hi> alwaies (as the Divell has) to doe Iſrael miſchiefe; But nor <hi>Eglon</hi> them, nor the <hi>Edomite</hi> now, no nor the Divell neither (mighty though he be) nor this Adverſary, nor that, nor the other, have ſtrength and power of themſelves, To doe <hi>Iſrael</hi> miſchiefe (for <hi>hurt</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe) I ſay, <hi>Will</hi> they have ſtill, <hi>Power</hi> they have none, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, till GOD lets it forth, till He ſtrengthens them againſt His People, for their Sinnes againſt Him, The <hi>God</hi> of all Wiſedome, Power, and Grace. So we Read: <hi>And the Children of Iſrael did Evill a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the fight of the Lord.</hi> [Obſerve that expreſſion by the way, and you will obſerve That <hi>God</hi> Markes what is done amiſſe, Hee ſees Sin in His People, for you Read here and every where, <hi>before the Eyes of The</hi> LORD,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 3.12.</note> 
                     <hi>in the ſight of the</hi> LORD.] <hi>And The LORD</hi> ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Eglon againſt Iſrael.</hi> Why? It is repeated againe, <hi>Becauſe Iſrael had done Evill in the Sight of The</hi> LORD: Therefore <hi>Eglon was ſo ſtrong</hi> againſt Iſrael then, The Edomites after that time; and now at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time, are ſo ſtrong now. That is the Reaſon The Sripture gives and it is a full Reaſon. Does the Enemy prevaile? Iſraels Sinnes doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile. Sinnes are ſtrong, and hands are weake; Mighty ſinners, and then mighty Adverſaries! Does the Edomites rage reach up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Peoples Sinnes reach thither too. Doubtleſſe if the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite have ſucceſſe in any Quarter of the Land, <hi>God</hi> does not doe it to gratifie the Edomite, but the more to confound the Adverſary, and to fit or make His People meet for Deliverance. Does Deliverance ſtay? It is That <hi>Praiſe may wait for</hi> GOD <hi>in zion;</hi> when the Worke is done, and Iſrael is humbled before his GOD, then the Edomite ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:155295:14"/>fall and riſe no more: The <hi>Lord</hi> will utterly <hi>undoe him:</hi> this belongs to the next Section. The Edomite has not yet fully executed his <hi>Commiſsion</hi> not compleated his Slaughter, There are <hi>Oxen,</hi> and <hi>aſſes,</hi> and <hi>Sheepe</hi> Remaining, and theſe he will ſmite with the Edge of the Sword in Revenge of <hi>David</hi> becauſe hee has eſcaped his bloody Knife: The Bruit Creatures fare the worſe for <hi>Davia</hi> now; but theſe groane under the Edomites hands. The Oxe, I cannot ſpeake little of him, therefore I will ſay nothing, but <hi>much increaſe by the ſtrength of the Oxe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.4.</note> And much good Service is done by the <hi>Aſſe;</hi> The <hi>Sheepe</hi> Cloatheth us with her Fleece, and feeds us with her fleſh, It <hi>is Man That hath ſinned, and done evill indeed, but as for theſe Sheepe, what have they done?</hi> Sayes <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> grieved for his poore People ſlaine with a grievous Plague, Gods <hi>Sword,</hi> which he had called for to leſſen the number of People, wherein <hi>David</hi> boaſted. We may ſay as much now and without a Figure, VVhat have theſe done? VVas the Edomites Rage againſt theſe poore Creatures? No, it was againſt <hi>David,</hi> or rather, for ſo <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids Lord</hi> is pleaſed to take theſe Inſolencies and wrongs done againſt David, as done to Himſelfe, <hi>Thy Rage againſt Me.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19.27.</note> Therefore the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the <hi>Lord</hi> have boldneſſe, and aſſured confidence, That their <hi>Lord</hi> does even now deale with this <hi>Beaſt,</hi> as he has done with his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-<hi>Beaſt,</hi> He puts <hi>an Hooke</hi> in his <hi>Noſe,</hi> and <hi>a Bridle in his Lips</hi> even Now.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Verſe</hi> 28.</note> And His People will give their LORD <hi>no reſt</hi> touching this matter, ſaying <hi>Ariſe O Lord in Thine Anger, lift up Thy ſelfe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 7.6.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe of the Rage of our Enemies, and awake for us to the Iudgement, which Thou haſt commanded. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Weighty Reaſons, Why The <hi>LORD</hi> ſuffers the Edomites to lay waſt Iſraels Land; how it Relates to this time. If Wolves had not beene grievous to our Land, they had not been deſtroyed out of the Land.</head>
                  <p>VVHy does GOD ſuffer an Edomite to deſtroy Iſraells Land?<note place="margin" type="runSum">Qu.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is there not a Cauſe?</hi> Sayes David in another Caſe; ſurely yes,<note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſ.</note> and a Cauſe for this alſo, an excellent Reaſon,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.29.</note> for what The <hi>Lord</hi> does or Suffers to be done though wee could give no accompt of it. Firſt,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Becauſe Iſrael may be growne wanton and carnally ſecure. A little <hi>Reſt</hi> from their Enemies, will make Iſrael ſettle upon their Lees: Iſrael cannot, I ſay Iſrael, <hi>Gods</hi> owne people, cannot well and Thrif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:155295:15"/>husband their time and peace. They may do it after they have felt the Edomites hand and have <hi>reſt</hi> from his oppreſsing Sword.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 9.31.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt have a Scourge, a Thorn in his eye and a Goade in his ſide. And none more <hi>pricking Briars</hi> nor any more <hi>grieving Thornes,</hi> then an Edomite is,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezck.</hi> 28 24.</note> That knowne Adverſory to Iſrael. Iſrael will not <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>their GOD:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 12.8.</note> Therefore he ſhall <hi>know</hi> the <hi>Service</hi> of a cruel Lord, that delights in <hi>Proud Wrath;</hi> An eaſie yoake made Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el wanton. An Iron yoake ſhall make them groane. Iſrael will bee ſtout with their <hi>God,</hi> and comply with an Idolatrous People, and learne the manners of the Heathen, play away the <hi>LORDS day,</hi> and <hi>ſnufe at His Service;</hi> will Iſrael do ſo? The <hi>LORD</hi> will meet with them for this; Hee will deliver them into the hand of them, whom Iſrael hateth, into the hands of them, from whom Iſraels <hi>Minde is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIENATED,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 23.28.</note> 
                     <hi>Prelates, Edomites, Atheiſts, Papiſts</hi> and the like, and theſe ſhall deale <hi>hatefully</hi> with Iſrael, they ſhall take away all <hi>Iſraels labour,</hi> and ſhall <hi>leave</hi> Iſrael <hi>naked and bare.</hi> This Relates it ſelfe, I need not ſhew how it relates to this time.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Edomite muſt be a plague to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Why? becauſe the Edomite is become a Lord and Maſter in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that he is <hi>ſet over the Servants of</hi> Saul,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.9. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 12.6. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 106.</note> if you obſerve it, he is next to the King, the greateſt man in Court, who but the Edomite there! he does all, all muſt come through his hand. The Edomite muſt be a plague to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> it muſt be ſo. Will <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuffer their Maſter <hi>Saul</hi> to take an Edomite to his ſide, To make him his right hand, <hi>dominus factotum, LORD do all,</hi> as the Proverbe is; will <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſuffer this? They ſhall have enough of the Edomite, that they ſhall; and <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall ſee there is mighty reaſon it ſhould be ſo; and when they ſee their Cities burnt with fire, and the Edomite<note n="a" place="margin">Iſrael ſaw with open eyes, That <hi>Saul,</hi> riſing-up againſt <hi>David,</hi> could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide an honeſt man: but his heart clave in love to the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, he ſhould have the honour of Knighthood, and of Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall in the held.</note> ſlaughtering them like Sheep; then they ſhall ſay, The <hi>LORD is righteous;</hi> yes, and gracious to <hi>Iſrael</hi> too, for</p>
                  <p n="3">3. By ſuffering the Edomite to deale with <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſo hardly, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to all the deſire of his ſoul, The good <hi>LORD</hi> will make the Edomite hatefull to all <hi>Iſrael, Iſraels</hi> mind ſhall be <hi>alienated</hi> from him; he ſhall never be entertained at Court any more; The Edomite ſhall well perceive as the Amonitedid, <hi>That hee ſlanke before</hi> David <hi>and all</hi> Iſrael: he has ſhamefully abuſed <hi>Iſrael</hi> this once, hee ſhall never ſerve them ſo again; he ſhall ſee how he ſtinkes before <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh! there is mighty reaſon why the Edomite in theſe daies ſhould deale ſo hatefully with Iſrael now; for all the Reaſons aboveſaid, (which I will not recall) and for this eſpecially, <hi>That he may STINK before David.</hi> and all Iſrael; ſo as Iſrael not abiding his <hi>ſavour</hi> any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger will joyne hand, and ſhoulder, and heart and all to thruſt him out of the Land, where they have committed ſuch abominations and executed ſuch wrath with ſuch a rage. Indeed it is good for Iſrael to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:155295:15"/>feel the weight of the Edomites hand; and the miſchiefe of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell: It was good for Iſrael then, it is as good for Iſrael now, to be ſo waſted by Edomites. VVho but the Edomite, before, in Court, City, Countrey? In the Court chiefe Commander there, and <hi>Keeper</hi> of the <hi>great Seale</hi> hard by; <hi>Recorder</hi> in the City, and Lord Generall in the Field: VVho but the Edomite all this? <hi>Dominus fac totum, Lord Do-all</hi> as was ſaid before. But the Edomite has ſmitten Cities, and burnt Townes, <hi>They ſtinke before David and all Iſrael now,</hi> and they muſt needs know it, that Iſrael will, in good time, riſe up all as one man to thruſt them out of their land. It is good for Iſrael that the <hi>Edomite</hi> has dealt ſo <hi>hatefully</hi> with them, waſting their Cities, and ſlaughter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their people. VVe would not lift up a ſword againſt the <hi>Edomite,</hi> to drive them out of the land, <hi>without gaine of money,</hi> (not yet) which the heathen in ancient time, and now, ſcorne to take, <hi>fighting againſt Iſrael.</hi> The time will come very ſhortly,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudges</hi> 5.19.</note> after the <hi>Edomite</hi> has vexed us a little more, that we ſhall willingly offer our ſelves, and jeopard our lives to the death to be avenged of the <hi>Edomite</hi> for our two eyes, (he would have put them both out) our burnt Cities, and waſted Townes. It was commonly ſaid, that there never were any VVolves in England, for that the Land would not beare them: Yes, there were VVolves in <hi>England</hi> ſayes <hi>Camerartus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 28.</note> and the Land yeelded the Wolves good and cleane feeding the beſt <hi>Mutton</hi> in all the Country, they feaſted upon it every Night. This Man loſt 20 Sheepe in a Night, another as many more. <hi>Grievous</hi> Wolves indeed. The People then did not ſtand looking one upon the other. Complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of their loſſes; Nor did they commit the ſlaughter of theſe Wolves, ſo grievous, to their Shepheards, Thoſe <hi>undertakers;</hi> who could looke to their owne ſafety, ſleepe all Night, leave the Wolves to their Prey, and take <hi>gaine of money</hi> in the Morning. No it was not ſo; every Man ſtood-up for himſelf, To keep the Wolfe from his Doore, and from his Fold, Tooke his weapon in his hand, and ſo purſu'd the Wolves; And it was gaine ſufficient to rid themſelves of them, and ſecure their Folds. And ſo they did their worke quickly, being every Mans worke, and beſtirring themſelves about it. Only this help was granted them, That <hi>Offendors,</hi> ſo be they were not Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, Capitall Offendors ſhould have their lives granted them and their liberty upon Condition, <q rend="inline">That they would bring in ſo many wolves thier <hi>heads</hi> or their <hi>Tongues,</hi> elſe the People could not believe they were killed.</q> By this meanes there was a cleane riddance of Wolves untill this day.</p>
                  <p>For ought I know, had not the VVolves been, after their manner, grievous, The Land had beene peſtered and plagued with them as at this day. Bleſſed be <hi>GOD</hi> ſay I, That VVolves are grievous, whether
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:155295:16"/>they have foure feet, or but two, they are wolves, and grievous. Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be <hi>God</hi> for that; That the Prelates hands were ſo heavy; Their Yoke ſo unſupportable; Their Orders, Their Oaths, their Courts ſo vexatious, miſchievous and unſufferable. Bleſſed be GOD, That Clergy and Laity, Miniſters, and people both, did groane <hi>for anguiſh of Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Cruell Bondage,</hi> under thoſe Taskmaſters doing the worke of an IMPERIOUS WHORISH WOMAN.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.</note> I verily believe we ſhall never ſee <hi>Prelate</hi> more in England, I ſay <hi>Prelate,</hi> A <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> I meane, (ſuch as our <hi>Biſhops</hi> were; Therefore the Name (though a good Name) is ſo hatefull,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Iohn</hi> 9.</note> becauſe ſo abuſed, ſo ill Anſwered) who <hi>love to have the preheminence,</hi> honour amongſt Men, and therefore cannot <hi>love</hi> the LORD JESUS CHRIST. We ſhall never have ſuch <hi>Biſhops</hi> againe (That word will pleaſe beſt) they were ſo grievous once: Sith they were ſuch grievous Thornes by nature it is well they were ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, That the Thorne was thruſt home. And ſo for theſe <hi>Edomites</hi> too. They will make their owne ſavour to bee abhorred in the Eyes and Noſtrills of all Iſrael. They are about their worke as faſt as they can, Bleſſed be GOD for it ſay I; for when there is no Peace to him that goes forth, nor to him that comes in: But <hi>great vexation</hi> ſhall be upon <hi>all the Inhabitants</hi> of the Countries. What then? Why then wolves are grievous, and then let the Country-Men alone, every one will ſtand in his place, The Man and his VVife both; Sonne and Daughter alſo, every one with their weapon in their hand; what it is I cannot tell, but what comes next to hand, that ſhall be a weapon good enough, for indignation againſt the Edomite, and his oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (which makes a <hi>Wiſe man mad,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 77.</note>) will frame him a weapon ſooner then all the Smiths forges in the Towne or City. Is it a diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thinke you, That their Armour is taken from them? None at all; Courage. Zeale for GOD, hatred of the Edomite, Love to their gaine and eaſe (I ſhould not put that laſt) all this is Armour of proof, the beſt Armour in the World. Doubtleſſe this was good to Iſrael, even to feele the weight of the Edomites hand, and the Miſchiefe of his Counſell: That Iſrael might have no communion with him ever after. It was good for Iſrael then to be ſo waſted by Edomites, ſo it is with Iſrael at this day, for Iſrael will deale with Papiſts as with their ſinnes, give entertainment to them, put them into Office, ſuffer them to beare rule, and ſway all there, as you heard, and their hearts to cleave to them in love; even ſo with their ſinnes, till they ſee and feele what miſchiefe their ſins have done them, what Lords, or luſts they have ſerved, and ſo what <hi>Fightings</hi> they have cauſed without, what <hi>feare</hi> within: And when they ſee and feele all this, then they can abhorre their Sins and themſelves, for giving ſuch loving enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment to their Sins ſo long. <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt feel firſt, and their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:155295:16"/>muſt be ſuffered to deale proudly, To prepare Inſtruments of death, and then to thruſt them home even unto the heart of Iſrael. Then Iſrael will open their eyes and look about them, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. To conclude. The Edomites muſt be as pricking Briars and grieving Thornes, before they ſhall be thruſt away: They muſt bee not in ſome but in all places, as evening VVolves, before every Mans hand will be thruſt out againſt them to thruſt them to the heart: They muſt <hi>ſtinke before David</hi> and <hi>all Iſrael,</hi> and then Iſrael will riſe up all as one man, to thruſt them out, who ſay of Iſraels Kingdome at this day as in ancient dayes <hi>Raſe it, raſe it even to the ground.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now here is a ſtrange ſight, Though the Edomite has dealt ſo cruelly with Iſrael as we heard, though he has laid waſte Iſraels Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and dwelling place, yet Iſrael, neighbouring thereabouts, come-not-in to helpe their Brethren, under the hands of a cruell Lord and a bloody Edomite. VVhat might hold backe the neighbouring Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite from comming-in to ſuccour their poore Brethren? That is the queſtion, and I deſire heartily to be underſtood in it. I ſhall not queſtion, Why it was ſo long ere the <hi>Tribes</hi> came-all-in to deliver <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> for then I ſhould queſtion the <hi>wiſedome</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> wherein I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied, and do thinke I ſhall be able, by the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie others in that point, and to give excellent Reaſon why <hi>David</hi> could not bee delivered one day ſooner then he was; which, being handled, as I hope by Gods ſtrength it may bee, will give mighty eſtabliſhment and encouragement to Iſrael, touching the diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent time.</p>
                  <p>My queſtion will be this firſt, VVhat might hold back neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Iſrael from comming-in to help their Brethren and Siſters now in the day of their trouble, and tredding downe by the foot of pride? The anſwere to this queſtion is, CONSCIENCE did with-hold Iſrael then, and the ſame CONSCIENCE muſt with-hold Iſrael now, in the very ſame caſe, from comming-in to ſuccour their oppreſſed Brethren; So ſayes Doctor <hi>Ferne,</hi> I will name him to comfort and refreſh the Divel and his Servants, his Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites in their war againſt the LAMB (for they ſhall have hot ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of it.) and to honour their cauſe, that they have not onely a <hi>Maſter</hi> but a <hi>Doctor</hi> in Iſrael on their ſide, a conſcientious man, who is as he ſayes, and makes men beleeve, a man of a tender ſpirit, he can behold Cities waſted, Townes fired, Men, VVomen, Children, Sucklings, Oxe, Aſſe, Sheep, ſlaughtered there, and, <hi>tender Soul!</hi> he is moved as much as a Rocke beaten upon with the waves: But if ſo be one or more ſhall lift up their <hi>hand for David,</hi> and to help him in the day of his diſtreſſe, with <hi>Bread</hi> and with a <hi>Sword;</hi> or lift up the ſword for <hi>David,</hi> then the good man melts, and good ſoule his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:155295:17"/>is troubled; O! ſayes he, beware what yu doe, <hi>yu reſiſt the King:</hi> Clap your hand upon the breaſt, conſult with <hi>CONSCIENCE,</hi> remember the Battle, and doe no more ſo. A man of a tender ſpirit no doubt! Let him alone, we know him well enough, he is wiſer, <hi>in his owne conceit then ſeven men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.16.</note> 
                     <hi>that can render SCRIPTVRE</hi> and <hi>REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON</hi> both for what they doe.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not goe a ſtep out of my way to meet with this good man, that has ſo tender a conſcience. Onely this, (for the Hiſtory leads me directly to it) I muſt neceſſarily doe, and by GODS helpe and His <hi>good WORD</hi> I ſhall doe it to purpoſe, and make good, <q rend="inline">That, had Iſraels hand beene with <hi>David</hi> now, and beene ſo bold and ſtrong, as to have been able to have wreſted the <hi>Commiſsion</hi> out of <hi>Sauls</hi> hand, which he was giving into the <hi>Edomites</hi> hand; and the <hi>Sword</hi> out of the Edomites hand too; had any Iſraelite done ſo, he had ſhewn as great a kindneſſe to <hi>Saul</hi> the King, and done as great a ſervice to his Kingdome, as is imaginable.</q> Therefore CONSCIENCE could not hold backe Iſrael from helping The LORD <hi>againſt the mighty.</hi> But this with much more, as I doe conceive, not without the Booke, of high and excellent concernment now, and will occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion a large diſcourſe, I muſt referre to the next <hi>Section,</hi> unto which I ſhall haſten as faſt as I can; Becauſe I have a ſtrong hope and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, That I ſhall be inabled therein to <hi>nonplus</hi> the Divell, and put his <hi>Edomite</hi> cleane out of office, if <hi>Law</hi> will bee hearkned to, and the beſt Reaſon. For as <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> both did call-in and authorize all Iſrael to riſe-up in armes, in ſuccour of <hi>David,</hi> (at the laſt, when <hi>Gods</hi> time was come:) ſo it followes, That all Iſrael will move now upon the ſame grounds, and will not be ſlacke; And yet they ſhall have no allowance, to <hi>Reſiſt their King,</hi> but allowance granted them from Heaven and Earth, to reſiſt the evill Spirit, working mightily now-a-dayes with the Kings of the earth, and with their <hi>Edomites</hi> there carrying-on their great deſigne, to <hi>dethrone</hi> The LORD JE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST. But when I have all done, I have little hope, That I ſhall ſati fie the tender hearted-man. I meane Doctor <hi>Fearnes</hi> Tender Conſcience I ſuſpect rather I ſhall leave his Conſcience as I found it, if not aſleep, then ſeared. That I may begin I will end with this; Doe we that, which is before us, our worke and duty, with all our might; Set we our hands and our hearts thereunto; it is to help The LORD againſt <hi>the mighty:</hi> and we will not dare to make <hi>que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> for <hi>Conſcience ſake,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</note> 
                     <hi>having a good Conſcience, That, whereas they ſpeak of us, as of evill doers, they may be aſhamed, that falſly accuſe our good converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis ſecundae <hi>Sectionis.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
